Shayan Shafquat

Shayanshafquat

Al specialist with two years of expertise in fine-grained pattern recognition, engineering LLM security solutions and deploying ML models in transportation and e-commerce industries. Backed by a solid foundation in Applied Mathematics and Decision Neuroscience, I am currently developing and contributing to LLM-based applications.

Education

MSc. Computational Neuroscience, Cognition and Al

University of Nottingham

Integrated MSc. Mathematics and Computing

INDIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, KHARAGPUR

Sep 2024 | Nottingham, UK **TENTATIVE GRADE: DISTINCTION**

Jun 2020 | Kharagpur, IN

CGPA: 7.2 / 10.0

Work Experience

Enkrypt AI, Inc | AI Research Consultant (Part-Time, Remote)

Boston, US | Jun 2023 - Sep 2023

- Developed a malicious file scanner for python scripts and jupyter notebooks, focusing on securing the ML lifecycle
- Built a dataset for prompt injection and backdoor attacks to fine-tune LLMs for security and adversarial robustness
- Implemented demo-ready LLM security using RAGAS and NeMo GuardRails to counter toxicity, bias, and jailbreaks

ANI Technologies Private Limited (OLA) | DATA SCIENTIST

Bangalore, IN | Sep 2020 - Jan 2022

- Pay after ride user identification: Impact: Increased cashless ride by 5% with no change in default rate (2.5%)
 - Enhanced the feature store API to analyze the behaviour of 15M+ users to establish trusted user base of 0.5M
 - Trained an ensemble model (balanced bagging classifier) on trusted users, achieving an AUC score of 0.91
 - Predicted default probabilities on non-trusted base, whitelisting 8.7M users while maintaining the default rate
- Improvements in peak pricing module: Impact: Reduced conversion prediction error by 2.2%
 - Developed a recency-weighted heuristic fallback model for peak pricing during outages, minimizing loss
 - Built and deployed a bike peak pricing module for bikes using spatiotemporal cab data and regression model
 - Maintained modules for hotspot pricing and in-trip cab inclusion in supply signal, with automated reporting
- User level pricing: Impact: +1.5% GMV/bookings and improved net completion during COVID-19
 - Automated user-specific coefficients from conversion rates via **cron jobs**, enhancing **demand signal** accuracy
 - Validated the hypothesis that abrupt fare changes cause regular user churn through a control-test study
- Key collaborative contributions:
 - Traffic Lights Optimization: Achieved an 18.3% reduction in wait times by optimizing traffic light signals with a Deep Q-learning RL agent in the SUMO simulation, effectively minimizing congestion
 - System: Enhanced the in-house utility package, streamlining data preprocessing and retrieval from AWS S3

ANI Technologies Private Limited (OLA) | RESEARCH ENGINEER- INTERN Bangalore, IN | May 2019 - Jul 2019

- Feature-engineered partner's ride data, using decision trees to predict login hours and form homogenous cohorts
- Optimized incentives for each cohort independently, minimizing burn while considering constraints on login hour
- Conducted A/B testing in Pune and Kochi to validate and ensure the effectiveness of the incentive optimization

Technical Skills

Experience with: Python, C++, Git, AWS, Azure, Docker, Kubernetes, Streamlit, SQL, Linux, Bash, R, Hive, Spark, LaTeX, NEURON Python Packges: Tensorflow, LangChain, LlamaIndex, Numpy, Pandas, Scipy, Sklearn, Scikit-learn, Seaborn, PyTorch, PyNeuroML, NLTK Modelling: DQN, Dyna-Q, RAG, Transformers, RNN/LSTM/GRU, VAE, GANs, CNN, Gradient Boosting, Linear Regression, SVM

Stochastic models of exploration in patch foraging tasks ☑

MAY 2024 - SEP 2024

Guide: Prof. Mark Humphries | School of Psychology | University of Nottingham

- Simulated foraging behaviours with resource depletion models and compared leave time predictions to MVT
- Evaluating stochastic action selection algorithms like epsilon-greedy, mellowmax using human patch-foraging data

Machine Learning in Science | Coursework

UoN | Oct 2023 - Present

- Developing 2D drone navigation with reinforcement learning
 - Tuned heuristic approaches and created a discretized action space for rapid movement and stable landing
 - o Trained and evaluated DQN, Q-learning models on average steps taken, fuel consumption and average thrust
- Optimizing CNNs for real-time autonomous driving on AutoPicar
 - o Developed CNN models using transfer learning for speed and angle prediction, addressing class imbalance
 - Enhanced model performance through data augmentation, architectural modifications and data collection
 - o Deployed the tensorflow lite models on toy car with TPU and camera, testing on three tracks and 12 scenarios

Neural Dynamics and Disease Modelling <a>C

SEP 2023 - MAY 2024

- Extended a neural network model that simulated **Alzheimer**'s disease progression within evolving brain networks
- Recreated multiple-frequency brain model, simulating neural dynamics and analyzing **resting-state brain activity**
- Simulated UP/DOWN state dynamics during **NREM sleep** in rodent brains, analyzing neural stability and transitions

Conversion of large-scale cortical models - INCF

GOOGLE SUMMER OF CODE 2022

Mentor: Prof. Padraig Gleeson, Ankur Sinha | UCL London

- Converted the channels, morphological and biophysical properties in L5 pyramidal cell from NEURON to NeuroML
- Implemented GitHub Actions to ensure the multi-compartmental cell model's behavior during development

Al Ethics and NLP Research | Self-Motivated

IIT KGP | Dec 2018 - Feb 2020

- Fairness-aware data representation: Reimplemented the iFair framework, minimizing utility and fairness loss, improving fairness by 3% and 9% with a 7% and 1% accuracy trade-off on Census and German credit datasets
- Rumour detection in tweets: Utilized one-hot encoding on characters to represent both tweets and comments, trained a CNN on named entities, and classified using a GRU, achieving a 68% accuracy
- Hyperpartisan News Detection: Designed and evaluated a self-attention model for bias classification in the SemEval 2019 competition, outperforming the benchmarks set by HCAN and Empath models

Relevant Coursework

• Offline: • Regression and Time series model

Data Structure and Algorithm

Neural Computation

• Online: o Linear Algebra by Prof. Gilbert Strang

- Practical Biomedical Modelling
- Object Oriented Systems Design
- Stochastic Process
- Statistics for Applications by Prof. Philippe Rigollet

Achievements

- Eligible to receive the **INSPIRE** scholarship by the Ministry of Science and Technology for the undergraduate study
- Gold winning LSTM model comparing India's top mutual fund houses in the Inter Hall Data Analytics 2018
- Achieved 99.5 percentile score among 0.2M students who appeared in the JEE Advance examination